Heat.  Heat.  Heat.  Heat.  Good
night.  I'm Walter Terry and I bring you
another invitation from the
Invitation to Dance series.  The guest is
Rebecca Harkness, president of the
Rebecca Harkness Foundation and director of
the newly formed Harkness
Ballet and Harkness House for the
ballet arts.  Mrs. Harkness is a
woman who in recent years has
dedicated much of her energy,
time, and devotion to the development of
ballet in the United States and to the
training of people for ballet.    She
practices ballet every day, not
because she wants to become a dancer
in her company, but because she wants to
know in her own muscles what
the dancers she
supports experience.
Well, I've always been interested in
dance and I've always done some kind of
physical work, whether it's yoga, athletics or
different types of dance.  When did
music enter your life?  I studied
piano as a child and about 20 years ago I
went back to studying piano
and with it I studied music theory and
harmony, and soon I started
composing popular songs.
Then, with your studies, you began to
delve into symphonic and
sweet forms.  Yes, I studied with Nadia Bulon and
Frederick Burley from Manis College,
and with other private tutors and
with Mr. Hby.
In other words, you did a real
job of training as a musician.
Yes, I've been studying that for 45 years.  In
recent years, I believe I am not
mistaken, through the
Rebecca Hartness Foundation, you have supported
international tours and
local performances of the Robert Joffrey Ballet, which
you presented in the Soviet Union with
tremendous success.  What deficiencies
did you feel, apart from the lack of money?
But to answer your question about
why I did this, I think there's only
one way.  There was a famous mountaineer
who said to him, "Why do you climb
mountains?"
Mhm.  Why are you going to climb Mount
Everest?  And he said, because it's there.
Then we ironed our own
suits.  We'll take care of the flowers.
We took care of everything that needed to be
done.  We washed our own
stockings and whatever else was needed.  But
we had these flower tins, these
tins where we kept our
flowers or, you know, things we wore
in our hair or earrings or something like that in
a separate tin box.  Joffrey got
angry when I got pregnant,
but I went on tour.  47 cities, right?
And he performed every night.
Well, you were in a pickup truck.  There were
six.  The original six.  You can't
imagine a truck with all this.
We were so cramped,
and their decorations were right on top of us.
Everything was on top of me
and one of the dancers was driving... I mean
, I was only three years old
and I mean, I was sitting down.  Yes.
And we couldn't stretch our legs.
The seats were like this.  And I can't,
if I had to sit like that, I'd go
crazy.  You know, Rebecca Harkness
was a wealthy woman.  She was married
to the king of Standard Oil.  Harkness
died.  She inherited a lot of money.
He knew many different artists,
loved music, and
considered himself an artist.  When Robert
Joffrey and she met, Joffrey
was in poverty.  He had no
money left.  It looked like they were going to have to
close.
And then, the Joffrey company
told us that we were going to do a
very special performance for someone and we
had no idea what was going on
.  But the Joffrey company
rented the Phoenix Theatre
downtown on Second Avenue, and
Joffrey said, "We're going to do excerpts
from the whole repertoire. So, you
know, all your costumes are here, and
we'll do a little rehearsal this afternoon,
and then you'll do the show
tonight."  And he said, "Well, here we go."
So we entered this theater which
was like a desert.  It was like
a very strange empty theater and
we started dancing and we danced all
afternoon and then we took a couple of
hours off and then we did the whole
program again and at the end of each
piece we made our formal vows, you
know, walk forward,
bow and walk backward.
Nothing.  We didn't hear anything.  There wasn't a
sound, not a sound.
We gave a short presentation for
a very important person who was
in the theater that afternoon to see
excerpts of the things we were
doing;  And it turned out that Mrs.
Hartness, and from there arose her
sponsorship of the Joffrey Ballet, took on
the financial burden of running the
company and making it possible.
Then she said, "Yes, I would like to
support your company, but I want you to
come and see Hill."  I think it was
10 weeks or something like that, something incredible
.  That workshop, I think also in
terms of what Harkness did, I think it's
one of the most
important things that happened in dance.
And then he understood, and Harkness
gave them that blissful and glorious summer
when they worked with Alvin A, Brian
McDonald, and Arpino.  It was an
incredible luxury, an incredible luxury to have had
that amount of time to be
able to do it.
Spending the whole summer there creating
new works, bringing in choreographers,
was very exciting.  For example, Alvin
A came and there were many others.  Even
Jack Cole came, Anna Sakolof.  I mean,
Bob Joffrey really
reached out to the modern community and
asked them to work for us.
We traveled a lot at that time,
sponsored by the
State Department, and we went to the Middle East, we went
to India, we went to Russia, Europe.
So that was very exciting for
the young dancers.  Heat.  Heat.    I
really didn't want her to influence
the type of ballets I was
doing.  He didn't want her to
have any say whatsoever in
his decisions as artistic director
of that company.  However, at the
same time, he had to negotiate and
manage his wishes for his music to be
used for different ballets.  And he
had to make a sort of
concession, something he didn't like
very much.  Harkness felt very
slighted by Joffrey when he did not
perform her ballet on one of the
tours.  I think they
did it in the palace in Russia.  Well, firstly
, she often disagreed
with his tastes and I think she felt
slighted by him.  I think she felt that
he didn't really like her music or
her work.  I think it was something new in the United States
in a way.  How do
you deal with a patron who is an artist,
considers herself an important artist, and
wants to have a say in the work?
Things were getting sorted out.    I
believe, as far as I know,
Mrs. Harkness's lawyers
felt that it was appropriate,
since she was paying the bills, to
call it Harkness Ballet, but she still
wanted Mr. Joffrey to be the
artistic director, and that was
totally unacceptable to Bob.  And that's
where the break occurred.
Joffrey felt that what she
was asking of him was to
compromise and reach some
kind of agreement in which she would
have a say in artistic matters and be
obeyed.  And that wasn't what I was going to
do.  So he went to the press.
I wanted to change the name to Harkness.
He didn't want to change the name.  And
he had every right to.  Then he
retired
and we never heard from him again and
we were desperate because,
well, what?
Bob suddenly disappeared; he
simply wasn't teaching.  He would
answer,
and there comes a time when you discover that you are doing what you are supposed to
do.  Well, I
needed to get a job.  And he
would answer, and at some point he
discovers that you do what you have to
do.  Well, I needed a job.
In the
first two years that we were there,
at that time.  Yes. From the very
moment we were there for the
first two years.  Jano called us and we
always felt like we were part
of Harkness.  I mean, we
loved Bob, he was the most
talented guy in the world.  A
beautiful choreographer.  Unfortunately, we had to
raise funds for the company and I
think we lost some of that.  But anyway
, we were always Harkness, you
know, from that first
phone call and there was never any
transition, sir, you know, from
Joffrey to Harkness life just flowed for
us,
but I got a call from Jeano
Cheron, who was the general manager, he
worked for Mrs. Harkness, went to
her apartment on the east side and signed
a contract to go work for
her.  He called us and said, "We're
thinking of starting a company.
We intend to do it, do
you want to be a part of it?"  I said, "
Yes."  You know,
so the Hearts Ballet started
with a big fuss.  You know, there was a
lot of press and a lot of participation, you
know, people trying to find out, you
know, what the Hartness Ballet really was
and what kind of repertoire
we worked on, what we created.  There were
many dancers from the Joffrey who
went to Harkness, not all, but
many.  And you know, it was a
pretty strong company from the start.  My
name is Jack Venza, a name that
many of you here will recognize from
public television.  It is a name
that was behind 35 years of
artistic programming on
public television.  And among them was Dance in
America.  But what happened was that
I received a call from Bob Joffrey to
tell me that Mrs. Harkness had
offered to fully support them and that
they would be spending a whole summer in Watchill,
where she had a house.  I asked
Alvin Venza to create a piece and he
suggested you be the designer
because you had just designed something for
his tour when he went abroad.  I was
surprised that Alvin thought of it
.  It was based on a play
by Larkca, a dark drama about a
grieving family and the
mother and daughters' obsession with protecting themselves from the
outside world, and the youngest daughter
wanting to go out into the world
.  When we first talked about it
, I said to him, "Alvin, how do you
imagine this?"  He said, "Well, you know,
I guess we have to make
period costumes. They're all covered in black
."  And I said, "But they'll be able to dance in
those big skirts. They'll have to be
big, heavy skirts and all."    It
also meant that they were
very expensive suits.  They required a lot of
detailed work.  Our contracts were not
signed with Joffrey, but were
signed and paid by the
Harkness Foundation.  It became a very
important issue later on because when
Bob decided he could not accept the
fact that the company name
would change, he preferred to remove his
belongings and all of his possessions.  None
of us could really object
because all our payments were made by
the Harkness Foundation.  But
it meant that all new works
commissioned by Joffrey, apart from Gerald
Arpinos, belonged to the
Harkness Trust.  And so, when Joffrey
retired, Feast of Ashes went with the
first repairman of the
Harkness Company.
No. So the question is, who
owns art?  So, if she
paid for the sets and the costumes,
and if she did pay, you know, if she did, what did she
own that she paid for? You know? And nobody
really knew the answer to that?    This
was all new terrain and
new territory.  When you walked past
Carnegie Hall, you could hear tap dancing.  You could hear
Russians teaching ballet.  You could hear
someone doing opera.  You could hear it was
live.  You could just hear it in the
street.  The buildings were full of
dance classes.  Luigi owned a
dance center.  He taught jazz.  A great
jazzman on Broadway.  Dance was something
important.  It was Studio 54. I was in
VIP.  I didn't have to wait in line.
Well, I was in New York.  The drugs
were pure.  Sex was safer.    I auditioned
and they accepted me.  And the
next day I took classes at the
company and immediately went to see
the general manager, Jeano Cerrone, a
great man.  And I said, "They gave me back my
contract. I don't belong with this
company. Everyone was so much better
than me. They didn't give me back my contract.
They said I had to stay. I
started in the back. It took me
six years to get to the front.
Sebastian was the first ballet I was in
. And I put on this
long dress and we rehearsed for a minute and they
explained the ballet to me on stage
. People were yelling things at me and telling me
what to do. It was very scary. That's
how I started. So I was one of the
original members of the company,
a dancer who wasn't Joffrey and who
happened to be part of the company.
Some people didn't accept the new
situation. So the company
needed additional dancers. So
they held an audition and I got
a contract.
Right after I finished high school, I left
Chicago and went to New York. I happened to
hear about an audition
for the Harkness Ballet and, since I didn't
know much about it, I went to
the audition. The audition was conducted by Leon
Feen. George Scabine was the director.
Mrs.  Harkness was there, and
also a very tall man named Bob
Severs. They selected two girls for
the company, me and another woman
named Myioko Kato. We were both
quite tall. We thought
we probably got into the company
because Bob Severs needed
taller dancers.
Well, I know he's famous for many of
the things he's done on Broadway, and it
was intense. For me, I was pushed, and he liked me very much
. I remember one rehearsal in
particular where I cried, but he
pushed me a lot, and finally, I got my act together, got
angry with myself, and
did what he wanted. We were wearing
jazz shoes, so it was very
different and very intense. And I remember
the music was great. And, well, you can
see the lighting. It was a lot of fun.
Harkness was performing in the center of
Broadway, and I didn't know anything
about it. So, I decided to go see the
performance. Harkness really brought out
the contemporary side. I think
contemporary is... Today came from Harkness. I
mean, Joffrey was doing
things. Alan Aling was doing things
, but she organized everything.  During
intermission, I went out into the lobby and said, I do
n't mean anyone I know or anyone
, who's the director here? And
they said, oh, he's over there, Brian
McDonald. And I went up to him and said,
"Excuse me, but I'd like to be in your
company."  "
Well, is the policy to balance
classical works with those
we might call modern or with
modern intentions? Do you include
modern dance as well?
I strongly believe in both. I think
we should definitely maintain the
traditional technique,
but create our own ballets
for it and not do the old ones, which
everyone has done perfectly, and I
really don't see how we can improve on them
at the moment. And as for
modern dance, I think we've had some
wonderful productions, and I think
when the modern dancer comes in and
understands our technique and uses
our dancers as they can
, the combination of the two is
fascinating and very dramatic.
Well, it wasn't just me. My sister
Maria also told me that she
became a dancer. It was my mother.
She had always wanted to be a
dancer, and when we were young, she
was determined that we would be.
So I think I started dancing
when I was three. The one
I remember most was because we did a dance in
Barcelona because we were there for a month
, I think. It was a great success, and Mrs.
Harus was very pleased. I'd like to
ask you, since Harkness House
is opening soon, if first  You could
describe its physical properties as
a house. What's in it? And then,
what do you hope to fill it with in terms
of the art of dance and
related arts?
Well, I want the dancers to
feel it. To feel at home here.
And it is a house. And it has four
ballet studios.
Big ones, too, aren't they?
Yes. And each one a different color
to make it attractive. And the snack bar,
the massage room, and the showers. An
art gallery because I think
we can have different paintings on
display. And I think dancers
are too tired to go to museums.
But if we can bring them some of that, it will
help them develop as
complete human beings and artists.
Initially, when the
building opened, there was a big celebration,
a big cocktail party to which
my family and I were invited. There were a lot of
famous people. In the picture with me are Leon
Denelian, Alexandra Denila, my father
Igorus, and Luigi, the jazz teacher. And I
think my impression was that it was the
most elegant and grandiose building I
had ever seen, designed for the
arts and the  ballet. Sabo Dalu was her
close friend. He had made an urn
for her. A chalice where I suppose
her ashes were, with
butterflies that fluttered open and
jewels that closed again. And there
was always an armed guard
sitting there. Well, on the night of that
opening, I happened to be
walking from the dressing room to go up
the stairs and I was alone. I
looked up and Salvador Dolly, in a
black cape, came running down the stairs.
He had an ocelot on his shoulder and I
was so taken with him. I went and watched him
float down the stairs. It was magnificent.
We were in Barcelona and Mrs.
Harkness has quite a bit of experience with
Salvador Dolly. Well, in Barcelona,
we were at Vod Park and at that time it
was the 60s and they were doing happenings
and they had this huge
plastic bubble. In the bubble there were about
six of Harkness's dancers and
Salvador Dolly in the bubble. Inside he
started throwing paint on the sides of
the wall and painting us. And
then Salvador Dolly painted me and my
mother said, "Why don't you  Did you make
that jersey sign?  "So, we
all had a blue leotard and
time to paint."  And that's what it was
.  It was strange but fun.  He was
good.  Strange.  He had a lot of
strange concepts, and if you look at his
artwork, it's very extravagant, you know?  I don't
know why, but it was a pleasure to be a
part of it.  And
wonderful places, you know, dancing on the
Riviera in Canada and then being in
residence in Monte Carlo and taking classes
in the same studio.  In the same
building, you know, where Vicki runs
from the tower to jump onto the
train tracks, you know, I mean,
you're in that whole story where
the Ballet Roose was.  When
we were in Monte Carlo, all the
older dancers would tell us
younger ones, "We feel the spirits
here in the Tatra of Monte Carlo."  You know
, everyone liked the
greats who had performed on those
stages.  Imagine being in Monte Carlo,
living in the Elmage hotel, with
Prince René and Princess Grace on
the royal balcony.  A
very beautiful opera house with a luxurious stage that I had
never been to before.
We had to go through a maze to
get to this studio.  I went down the
corridor, turned left, went
under the velvet curtain, went out onto
the road, went back in,
went down a few more corridors to
this old, damp studio with
rotten floorboards and all that,
but that's where I used to rehearse
ballet.  So, you know, the dancing
was on the rafters.  And also on
our bums because, remember,
folks, we often did ballets where we were
dragged around and
splintered and, oh yeah, it wasn't ideal.
Heat.  Heat.  Stuart Hodes was a
dancer with the Graham company and
was trying to move into the world of
ballet, and it was also at that time that
people were experimenting
with modern dancers working
with ballet companies.  He came and
found my wife and me, Lona
E. Saxon and me, and wanted to do a
piece called The Abyss.
And I did the first duet, just the first
duet.  They were lost, you know?  Yes.
And they were a romantic couple.  It was
very much based on this story by Andrea,
The Abyss.
And they were having this discussion that
children would have, you know, does
love exist? Is it immortal? What is it?
All About Life and that was my
little ballet and
literally that's what it was,
but with Larry and
others, they also had
wonderful music, I finished the
first part and showed it to
Rebecca and of course Kabine was
there and they did very well in the
screening,
if I may say so.  It was a good
part to do.
My personal story about that is that
we were in K and we were going to do all
these premieres in K and George Cubin came
to pick me up after a rehearsal.
So, uh, I was in his car and he said to me,
"You know, I promised Eric Brun a
premiere and I haven't been able to keep my
promise, so I'm offering him the Abyss.
" Well, that was a very sad moment.    It
premiered in theaters and a couple of
weeks later in Paris.  I did
Abby and it was a huge success.
Good.  Brian became an
artistic director.  He saw in me that I could
move like lightning, right?
Even with smart people like
Brian McDonald, I mean, he
choreographed a trio for Helgi, Lon and
me, Zealous variation, which was
challenging, but where
you really felt like you were exploring and
using your body and mind.  Zealous
variation is simply a
classic powatto, a reaction to some
variations by Schubert for piano and
four hands that Mrs. Harkness
found and orchestrated for me in a
lyrical and brilliant way.  Now,
gently to the ground.  Hold it.
Hold it.  Hold it.  Good.  I'm going to leave the same way
you came.  Stay.  Everyone
had seen the Hartness Ballet, but
never New York.  So when it
was finally confirmed that the
Broadway theater would definitely be
ours for the first three
weeks of November—this is 1967—
well, it was like a birth, and it was a
relief and an anticipation for the
Hartnesses to show what they could
do in New York.  And he would rehearse and rehearse
and rehearse and probably not
rehearse 8 pounds of whatever it was for
a good half hour, an hour.    It
just kept going and going and going,
and it was always said to be a work
in progress because it was never finished.    What an
incredible experience!
What attracted me to ballet, what
really attracted me, was not making
ballets, but doing work that the
dancers felt really good
doing.  Song Night Song is based on
classical ballet but has a lot of
contemporary elements.  It is not a
pure classical ballet.  It is an abstract work,
but it has other things.  Below.  Hello.
Hello.  Rebecca Harkness was truly the
great patron of American dance
.  It was avant-garde.  He had very
passionate ideas about supporting
young dance artists, American
dancers and choreographers, American dance artists and
choreographers
, and
American composers.  I truly believed in the
talent that had developed in
our country.  shores.  Because this is
really the story of America
and American arts, and how
the arts are funded and how
funding affects the aesthetics and the
work you see on stage, because that's how it is
.  The New
York Times' chief critic was very much against her
.  It was an uphill battle, even
for us dancers, to be
recognized.  Kai Barnes wrote the
worst review and he wasn't looking at it
from an objective point of view.  It was
obvious that he had some kind of problem, and it goes back
to when Joffrey and Hartness
separated, and he basically took
sides, and the side he took was
Joffrey's, and he hated Rebecca Hartness and
the Hartness Ballet.  It's very obvious
when you read their reviews of the
company.  We live in a
capitalist society.  So where you get
your money is going to have an effect on the
art.  How does art affect the
economic,
political, and
social conditions of the United States?  There's a
feeling that it's something like what we
feel now with 1enters. You know,
you can do whatever you want.  You don't have to
try hard to achieve it.  You can
buy beautiful ballet flats, you can
buy costumes whenever you want.
You can buy space.  You can have
a school.  This is a time when
people buy art and see it as
a commodity, something you can
collect.  If you get ahead of the game, you might be able to
make some
money from it.  The good thing about Harkness
is that she's investing in
art, in art in general, and she was
investing in performing arts,
which is something ephemeral.  How does
patronage work now? Can one person
support an entire company?  No. No.
How often does a
small company perform these days? Do
they have big seasons?  No. No. It
takes a huge amount of money
to do that.  Is the school
open to the general public or
is admission by audition?
Right now admission is by
audition
and you want to give an opportunity to those with
a special talent.
I believe everyone should receive
special attention
because I believe it is the only way
they can develop.  But not in
a huge class of 40 people.    They
will also have some modern dance
.
Oh, yes they will.  That will come.
Character
and some ethnic dance and perhaps some
acrobatics for those who
need it to develop.  What about
the program they have for what
in Europe are called trainees or
apprentices? What is that supposed to do
?
I think they would be better understood if they were
given the same consideration as
interns in the hospital
just before people become
truly professional.  If they can gain
a year of experience performing, but not in
professional settings
and
without being subject to criticism, and
working with different choreographers, they
would be much safer than when they
joined the professional company.
Why can this person jump
higher than the next one? How is it
that this person can turn more than
the other?  Because before that, you know,
we were just qualified.  You're a
jumper, you know, or you don't jump at all.  You can't
do this, you know, you don't turn.    You ca
n't do this part;  We need
a lathe operator.  Many people thought that
anyone could learn to
do anything.  Well, Joanna was
a brilliant woman;  He was absolutely
brilliant and had a lot of
knowledge, especially about anatomy,
but he didn't really have that much
knowledge of kinesiology.  I knew what it was about
, but I wasn't an
expert.  I studied kinesiology.
So I taught
Joanna kinesiology to complement her anatomy,
which was an interesting project.
So we were going to Harkness.  Pat Wild
was the director.  Pat Wild was very
strict about what she believed should
happen, so she and Joanna often
had those discussions.  I got along
well with P. I was the ham and the
sandwich
because I got along well with Joanna, I
got along well with Fat Wild and I used to go back and
forth between them and Mrs. Harkness
wanted someone trained this
way to teach at the school and the
company.  So Mrs. Harkness
took David Howard and sent him to me in
Spain.  So I did
teacher training with David Howard for
three months in Spain and Mrs.
Harkness decided that he should be the one to
teach the company and, of
course, he had received
excellent training in England.
So David, very clever,
planned classes that incorporated
this, but without giving it a name or
talking about it, he simply put it in
combinations.  So he taught classes
at the Hartness company for years,
for a very long time.  Finest was one of
them.  Larry Rhodes was one of them.
Dennis Wayne was one of them.  They
were all in that company.  And even
those who said they weren't really
part of Joanna's group
absorbed a lot from David because that's
how he taught.  Those were four
very interesting years of my life.  Well,
Hartness' research and training session was one of the first
innovative dance training programs
.  The training program was
developed in such a way that, even
if you didn't have a perfect body,
you could move it very, very well, and everything
was geared towards movement.  And
we had kinesiologists and people who
worked with the body.  We had
the capacity to involve all the
medical staff who had something to
do with the movement.  And it evolved from
that desire to have a
much more informed way of doing things
instead of a cockroach-like way
because you have all these little soldiers
lined up that look alike.
The first few years passed and
suddenly we started having dancers
who were born coming out of the same
maternal womb.  One, two, three, four like that.
So, of course, they accepted us and
in one year we ended up incorporating
more dancers into the companies than
all the other
company schools combined.  I was like,
get on that bus.  Let's go and the
company goes to this farm or barn.
And we went and marched and entered that
barn, and we sat down.  And someone said,
just say there's going to be a vote,
so vote yes.  So I
agree.  And I believe there was a vote
to expel Brian.  I said, "Brian,
I think the question is, are you going to be
here with the company all the time?
Can you be here with the
company all the time now?"  And he turned
to me and said, "Yes, I will."    That's what
the whole meeting was about, you see.
After we finished, we went to dinner.
But that was, I would say, a sign of
what had been happening.  And I think it
was too late.  So
I said, "Okay, I'll get on a plane,
go to New York, and speak
to Mrs. Harkness personally."
And she said, "Do you know what you would do if
you were in charge?"  "Well," I said, "
I have some ideas too
."  In retrospect, it was probably
the first nail in the coffin for me.    It
was tough, no doubt.  And then I went to see
Mrs. Harkness and said, "I think
I need a co-director because doing
all the work I do as a director
and dancing all the time is too much. Way too much
."  So she said, "
Okay."  And I hired Benjamin Hawk
Carvy.  I think we were there in six years
.  I think we had
about six directors.  Some didn't
last long, and others a little longer.
I think being a director is probably
the hardest thing in the world.  And I don't think there's
a director who's happy
at the end of their term.  You know, I don't think
Larry was happy at the end
of his term.  And Brian, without a doubt, was
tough.  Harkness's young dancers
were a small group of
school people who basically
worked in
New York public schools.  They created a program.
Obviously, there were works that
Mrs. Harkness liked very much and
enjoyed being with.
Meanwhile, we were in Europe, racing
and having a lot of success, but of
course, costing money.
Well, it was an exciting opportunity
when Mrs. Hartness offered me
the job of directing the young
dancers.  On the one hand,
I loved the young dancers.  It was a way
to start.  I had never directed before
and although I had taught, this was a
great way to gain experience,
so I was really looking forward to it
.  When I look back on it, I don't consider it
a bad time, but a very
good time for me, which gave me great
opportunities, but there were also
strange undertones.  I don't know all the
answers, but she was
very involved in what the ballets would do and
who would choreograph them.  But I do
know that Bob Severs, Robert Sever,
had many things he wanted to
achieve with the company.  And I think he
also told me once that he
wanted to end up running one of the
companies, so I think he
had it in mind and he was also very good
friends with Mrs. Hartness.  So
the more they met and made
artistic decisions, not just about
the ballet, but about who would dance
in it, the more no one paid attention to
what she wanted.  We did a lot of
modern work.  She wanted more
classical works.  Although
we also did many classical works.  I think
the word going around was that
we spent a lot of time on the floor
rolling around on the floor and she was
basically a classicist, even though
she brought in people like Alvin and John
Butler, you know, to work with the
company.  She was done, and the
company was done too.
I think that in the end, in its
simplest form, this was his
ballet company.  This is what
she was paying for.  Each one of us,
all the ballets, all the theaters,
she paid for everything.  And I think she
just felt she could do what she
wanted to do.  But I know there was
a feeling that we were out
of New York for a long time.
We were touring Europe, but we did
n't actually do seasons in
New York.  And I know from others that
they felt this was detrimental to
the company.  At one point,
Larry Rhodess and Ben Harvey were
directors of the company.  They ran
the company and I seem to recall something
about them giving an
interview to the press.  What I heard
was that they thought it was unofficial and it was
n't published as unofficial.  And I don't think what they
had to say about Mrs. Harkness was very flattering
.  And I think that was one of
the reasons why he fired them.
What he did was have 40
dancers.  He got rid of 20. He wanted to
keep the other 20 to put them
with his second company of 20 and make
a company of 40. Of the 20
dancers he kept, 19 said
goodbye.  They fired the best director we
've ever had, Larry Rhodes.  Only
one remained.  And then we received the
telegram and that was devastating.  Our
last performance finished them all off.
Jeano, I hope it was Jeano and Arian,
Elizabeth's daughter, handed us
all over, we all went out to
bow and they gave each and
every one of us a red rose,
which took a long time.
How old was Ariana?  It took a long time.
And we were all crying and crying
and crying.  with Harkness Ballet.
Simply put, the entire company
disappeared, and suddenly only
the young dancers remained.  So it
was a completely
different company.  We were kids in school
and when I was with people like Janette
and Zayn, we were kids, apprentices
performing at the Delort Theatre, you know,
very good dancers, very good
kids.  I mean, but we were
young.
Many new ballets were made just
for the company and a very
different repertoire.  It wasn't classical ballet.  They
weren't just modern pieces.  It wasn't a
jazz group.  A truly
eclectic mix.
Basically, I only worked with Ben
Stevenson, Robert Stevens, and Sandy Debr.
That's all.  I didn't know anyone else, and
these are the same people who
trained me when I was 16.
Mrs. Hartness really wanted a
company with students
trained at her school.  Very similar to what
Ben Stevenson does in Houston, to
what Balanchin did.  You know, those were
times when you really wanted
a school where you could educate
your students to become
members of the company and have
the right style for you.
There was a sense of attracting talent
.  That talent was more important than anything
else.  Talent was the
primary factor in bringing dancers
to the Harkness Ballet, and that seemed to be
what attracted people to the
company as well.
Mrs. Hartness was fascinated
when she interviewed me and loved the
idea of ​​my culture and she loved
flamenco.  He insisted that the
company adopt flamenco, and
I remember saying, "Wow, this is a
ballet company."  I returned to New
York in search of work.  By
chance, I was watching a
performance at the Met.  I met
Mrs. Harkness and a gentleman named
Renzo Rice.  So I went back to the
company.  She was very small.  She looked about
12 years old.  She was tiny.    She was
only 1.52 m tall and very thin
and looked very, very young.  Renzo thought he
looked too young to be
in the company.  But Maria and David
really wanted me to be there
and I had learned this
classic Spanish solo on point and I played
the castanets very well and in the solo I did
fetes while playing the
castanets.  So I was a dun and my
arms were like this.  I am playing the
castanets.  I'm making the fountains
and playing the castanets and the rhythm.
So they made me do this one just
for Mrs. Harkness and she said she
wanted that girl in the company.
Several of us were taken to
New York.  I remember that we were children
, especially, like three, four,
five children.  Rebecca had a
dance festival that was part of
Joseph Pap's Shakespeare in the Park, and
the apprentices performed.
And she was also that young and just
starting her career.  It was as if
the doors were opening to the magic of what it
truly was.
As much as the first company
was Mrs. Hartness's company
, the second company was her baby.
So Hog was different.  Everything he did
was new.  I did some of the
revived things and some of the
standard classical pieces, but
Sebastian Gemini, it was like it was all
for the Hawkins Ballet.  It was made
for the Hawkins Ballet.  If
a choreographer likes you or feels you're the
right person for him, he'll create a
ballet for you or whatever.  I really do
n't know how it came about.  All I know is that one
day I was in the lead
dance roles and I thought, "This is strange."
We could participate as apprentices in
the Firebird, but as
Russian icons we were on top of
a 10-foot-high set that
moved around and we had these heavy costumes
and we had to hold the trumpets
at the end for the wedding and I was very
scared.  This thing was kind of
shaking and I never dreamed that one
day I would get to play the
Firebird.  So for me it was a big
leap.  It was a little scary to do it
like a movie.  We traveled to Berlin
to do it.  We spent several weeks,
I think a few weeks, if I
remember correctly, rehearsing on a
stone, cement floor, which was the
small space of the film studio.  So it
was very different from doing it on
stage.  And Vicente was a kind
of exotic creature to me.  A South American who
spoke in a funny language.  He had
a long mustache.  He was smoking a cigarette and
talking at the same time.  Half in
Spanish, half in English.  The idea was
that we would have these men in the
school and in the junior company and
say, well, it was like, let's
showcase them.  He was always very open
to making changes to adopt
new things from the dancers.  He always
worked on the dancer in
front of him.
I had a lot of instruments and
step by step and measure by measure we were going to
create a ballet
and also, being an unusual piece and
only percussion, it was very
exciting, very exciting for all of
us and also for him to be
there creating it and everything.  And for
us, it was, once again, a
growth experience to have gone through that and
that it is still alive and still being
performed today; I think that is
a testament to its enduring value.
Heat.  Heat.  When I went back to work
in the girls' ballet, it was a
little different.  I walked into the studio one
morning in the big room at RCA in
Madrid and it was then that
we discovered they didn't speak English and
I didn't speak Spanish, so
we decided it would be best to go back to the
United States and record there.  Without a doubt
, it was the most incredible experience of
my life because we went to Europe and we went
to all the places in Europe and we went to
all
the places in Europe in every way possible.  We took a
bus tour of Spain that lasted a thousand
years and stopped in every small town
to celebrate its saint's day.  The
stages were set up on
cafe tables that were all
connected by a lenolio above.
I did all the tours with the company
from 1970 to 1975. The tours
took us all over France, Spain,
Portugal, Germany, Italy, Greece and
Lebanon.  The problems on the tours
were mainly at
outdoor venues.  And when that happened, the
floor got very wet and became
slippery.  Sometimes we had to
cancel or have the stagehands
clean the floor.  We danced in certain
areas, like certain areas that had
theaters, others that had bullrings.
So they would set up a stage at the
end of the bullring, and it was like
a portable stage and our
dressing room.  I can imagine it.  Our
dressing room in one of the bullrings
was a huge room.  There was no
bathroom, you know, no bucket, whatever.  And
someone said we had to be
careful with the red suits, the
red capes, because the bulls were right
there, right next to us.
We had to walk past the bulls
on our way to the stage.  Yes.
So they flew us to
Gishad.  Mrs. Hartness had
bought a chalet which she had
converted into a studio, and the chalet next door to
the studio was her own
chalet where she lived.  So I joined
them at Balbeck and they had a strip
of stage that wasn't very big,
but I put them all on the rocks.  So
when they made entrances, since
we couldn't hide them like they had
done, you know, we didn't have the
lighting, the
sophisticated lighting that we had on this
precenium stage.  So I had to
re-stage their entrances, and
so on.  So I positioned them so that
you could see them coming down from
behind a column, descend
those steps, and finally reach
Marley's strip to do their
dance;  It was simply a
magical moment, a truly magical moment.
We traveled from Baalbeck to Greece, to
Athens, and there we danced in the
Herodatic Theatre, which is
located just below the Acropolis.
So, we were getting ready
to go from Athens to Paris.  We were
in our hotel and I don't remember
exactly if we were getting on the
bus or if we had been told to get
off because
war had been declared.  Türkiye had
invaded Cyprus.  So Greece
mobilized its army.  The airport
closed.  We felt like we were trapped in
our hotel.  We didn't know what was going to
happen next.  One day, Jeano Chiron
said: "Well, let no one say anything."
Grab your suitcases, go outside and get on the
bus.  "The bus took us to the
port of Corinth in Greece. And
apparently Mr. Chiron had
arranged for all of us to be born
on a cruise ship, an overnight ferry that
went from Corinth to Italy and then to Anka,
Italy. So we snuck onto the
ship, gave birth, and the ship took off,
and there we were on a
Mediterranean cruise. Did you have in mind the
great court theaters of Europe?
I think the setting is very important. I
couldn't just put in splashes of
gold, squares, or cubes. It was a
very exciting time. I mean,
we were opening a theater. I mean
, we were opening a
theater that was designed for
dance. Mrs. Hart bought an old
movie theater on Broadway and transformed it into an
absolutely exquisite theater. And the
stage was perfect. No
dressing room was more than a flight of
stairs away, a small flight of
stairs away. So you never
had to hurt your leg
climbing tons of stairs or anything like that
. She was very, very kind to
us. That night,
opening night, I did two ballets. One was
Sebastian de Vicente  Natrada, and the
other was Todd Bolander's Memories.
We were there for two weeks opening
the theater. So we performed
our entire repertoire.
The critics were very enthusiastic
about the dancers. They criticized the
theater itself. There were two
world premieres. Perhaps more than that,
Ryan McDonald's Rodan Bison V from The Lottery
. They'd
already had their opening night.
It was April 17th, it was my debut and it
was her birthday. She arrived in a
gold dress and her gold
Salvador Dolly tiara, which was like something
the Statue of Liberty would wear,
you know? It was a gold tiara with
Dolly's spikes. She was radiant and she'd
chosen it because she'd seen the rehearsals
. She wanted it for her birthday. This
was her birthday present. The
second night, which was April 21st,
they put Rodan last on the program
. At the end of the performance, they shouted
my name and it was like this
exciting moment, this somewhat
shocking moment. It was an
exciting moment. Really. I had some
ideas and I told Zayn and Linda, the
two  People who danced this: "
Can you come to the small studio?"    "
I want to see what something looks like." And that's
really what came out. I had some
things in my head and I wanted to see them. And it
seemed to me that every dance piece that
had a couple was about
anger or destruction. And I just kept
wanting to see some nice, romantic
happiness. So that's really what
came out. And Mrs. Harkness
liked it, so she said, "Well, let's
put it on."  Amen.  Of course, what
always comes to light is your
personal wealth, something that arouses people's
curiosity.  I think many other
people are given credit for
having much more money than me
because I can only carry a little.  Was it
your idea to find a way to help other
jazz companies besides your own?
Yes, I think we would create a board of
directors in France to compensate for the
deficit.
We left because it was time to leave.
We were hearing rumors that
Harkness wasn't doing well.  They found out
about our campaign, so
they tried to emulate it in New York to
raise money for the Hartness
Ballet.  And why didn't it work?
Because many people said, "Wait a
minute, wait. Why am I
donating to a billionaire?"  There was
a market downturn, especially with
regard to
oil stocks, and I believe that a large part of
Rebecca Hartness's fortune was
tied to oil.  Well, I no longer
had enough income.  He supported
other companies and ventures.    I
believe Pearl Primis received support.
Joseé Greco too.  He supported
performances in Central Park.  She was a
true philanthropist and put her money
where her heart was.
I believe Mrs. Hartness was very
ill at the time, and I think
when she opened the theater she was heavily
criticized for some of her
ballet choices.  There were some very
bad reviews about her.  I really didn't like it; I
think it was terribly
unfair that it was criticized.  Here I was
giving a beautiful theater to New
York.  I had a magnificent company,
one of, you know, there were only four
companies in New York at that
time.  And I think people,
mainly, I don't know, sometimes they were
just envious, maybe,
or they didn't think the company was
very good, whatever their opinion was.
But I don't really know what the
end of it all was, except that everything started
to fall apart in the mid-70s.
Basically, the issue was that there was
no longer a record company and we were going to
finish the US tour and
after that tour it was over.
Eve, the company dissolved in
1975. It was a very sad day for me.
I remember we were in Miami in
March of 1975 and during our
final bows we were all
crying and it was horrible.  But anyway,
because everyone went their separate ways and a great
era had ended, and Mrs.
Harkness was so wonderful to
us, and well, it was a sad time
.
It was a volatile time, you know, as
exciting as it was.  However
free and spontaneous
things were in many ways, there was a
growing tension after the 60s and
70s. Things got a little more
tense, a little more serious, a little
more back to routine and
traditional customs.  In the 80s and
90s, it became much more fashionable for
entrepreneurs not only to invest
financially in ballet, but
also to attend ballet, opera,
and symphony concerts.  That's why I believe that if
that hadn't happened and there hadn't been
more corporate support,
we should look back on Ms.
Hartness with great appreciation.  I saw
Harkness, I think in '72 or '73, in
Nice, France, and it was incredible.  So
when Nikita Town came and saw the
rehearsal, she said, "Do you want to come and
work with us? I'm planning to
set up Hartness Dance Studio, which is
a youth version of what
the company used to be, because we don't
have the same funding now."  And Rebecca (
Mrs. Hartness) wanted to do something,
so I said, "I'd love to."  So
I came to teach a few classes and then
they made a contract and that meant my
first work permit to come to the
US. But the first 6, 7 or 8
months, if I remember correctly, were
exciting because there were a lot of
talented people.  I was the last group
Rebecca applied to for the
Harkness apprenticeship program.  And
that was maybe in '76, I think it was
'75 or '76. And Christopher Aante came to
lead the tour in Taiwan.  And it was
simply incredible.  I'd never
worked with anyone like that before.  When I
left Harkness, I danced with the Kansas
City Ballet under Todd
Bolander and then with
Mary Day's company, the Washington Ballet with Chan
Go.  And I've been at my school for about 30 years
.  And I
went from the
Houston Ballet's second company to becoming David
Howard's apprentice at Harkness in 1973. I danced with
several incarnations of Harkness, one
with Alonso Kout and Willie Burman, and then I
returned years later with Robert Severs
and Nikita Talin, and now I'm a chef.  I have
two stars in the New York Times.
Well, I run a jazz club and I have
a secret dinner club called 10
Chairs.
I was there when
many changes were taking place.  Maria, it was
the end of Maria Ba's time there,
while David Howard remained
at the venue for another year.  Then he left
and Reita Extter took over
when Willie Burman and Alfonso
Kata arrived and we did Ballet on Broadway, which I
believe was the last performance
the Hartnesses did in a
professional theater.
Yes, it was at the Beacon Theater.  Then they
left, then Bobby
Severs and Nikita arrived, and I think it was
exactly at that moment that I
left.  I think that's when I
left.  I make a living by making tutus
, which is a lot of fun.  Every time I
say it, I can't believe it.  No.
When I was at Harkness, we had
lots of old tutus that had never been
washed or cleaned because there was no
one in charge of the
wardrobe.  I remember that I used to smuggle them in
.  I shouldn't tell
anyone this.  I used to
smuggle them in my dance bag,
take them home and put them in the
washing machine, you know, wash them.  Ruth
Petrin and Maria Vy taught in
very different ways.  It wasn't
just about pointing with your feet,
standing up, and putting your arm this
way.  It was a very
kinesiological study of how the
body moves.  But I also believe that the
musicality he taught us was
because we had great pianists.
We had some wonderful students,
Ray Wilson and John Charles, who were
fantastic.  They didn't just play "1, 2, 3,
4, 1, 2, 3, 4, 1, 2, 3, 4";  They continued
like a sonata, and you had to go and
phrase it.  But it was a different way
of learning to count music, and
musicality was a very
important part of how we were taught.
Using the laws of physics, even if
you had all those
different teachers, there was such a cohesion
that, by attending the class in the morning
and then the one you had in the afternoon,
you could perceive a clear
continuation between both sessions.    It
always made sense.  And then, in the
end, it didn't make sense anymore.
And Nikita was a very
controlling person, and I think it was at that
time that Rebecca's health
was failing.  She wasn't really
involved in school at all anymore, and she'd
always been, you know, involved in
school.  He came to the performances,
he came to all those things and he
was always there and, for whatever reason
, there was nobody to stand up to
.  There was no one to tell me I couldn't
do this or
that.  So you and some other
people need that.  Some
people need that kind of
focus, and Nikita wasn't a
focused person.  He just had to go
there once, do this, and we'll
call it scrambled eggs.  I'm not
kidding.  She would spend
hours and hours splitting up, you know,
lighting cigarettes under the pain
of her legs.
That's true.
After Reita Exter left,
because Maria left, David left, Ann
left.  Everyone was fine.  Back then they
were all new and I'm not sure they
knew each other, you know?    It
was like people came in, taught the
class, and left, right?  Each one
on their own.  It was no longer a
cohesive school.  It was just a group of
teachers.
When I arrived, Rebecca was already
quite ill.  Mrs. Car. And
then they were more like, how do
we make the transition without her
leading this ship to a
viable organization that would produce, you
know, according to her wishes, her
hopes, and her dreams?  What
we did were choreography workshops
and David Parsons, who now has his
own big company, did his first
choreography in Studio B, some
Spanish music.  It was always
Rebecca's baby, even until her death and
even after her death, because it
remained a difficult underlying operation
.  And I went upstairs,
sat down and talked to Nikita, and that same
day I was given a full scholarship.  And
then I told Nikita that I
was actually a choreographer.  When I finished my
second ballet there,
roommate A. Well, supposedly I talked to you
about mental illness, but she did it
in such a funny way that people
laughed the whole time.  I didn't know if
they understood the message, but they
did.  And I was sitting in the
cafeteria, with my back to you, wearing my
bow tie and my Versace jacket.
I thought it was so cute.  And he was standing with his back
to the door and talking
to the dancers.  We were having a
good time and suddenly the whole room
went silent and a hand
landed on my shoulder.  Mrs.
Hogness said, "Keep it up."  And
then he turned around and didn't speak
or look at anyone else and just
left.  Well, getting the urn out of the niche where it had
been placed turned out
to be a really crazy production
because there had to be someone on the
fourth floor doing certain things,
electronic things that were
coordinated with someone in the basement
doing certain things.
They finally managed to open the urn.  So they
took it upstairs and there they had made a
small container to put it in because it
was a clockwork mechanism.  I mean, I
had butterflies that opened
and twirled and all that stuff.
So if you looked inside there were like
cobwebs or wires and stuff in there
, but they made a small
container that really wasn't
big enough for half of
it.  So Robert took the
waxed paper out of the box with the edges and
literally shook it into the
urn, put the chalice back in the
urn, and everyone left.  When I was
researching all the material about
Rodan's life to make the ballet, it was
very important for me to get to know him, to
know what his character was like and what
his life was like.  All of that was very
important for my dialogue about each
of the pieces.  He wanted the kiss
to reflect his relationship with Camille
Claudell.  She was a young sculptor
and they began a very, very,
very passionate relationship.  She wanted him to
leave Rose Beret, who was his partner.
He didn't do it.  This kiss is, for me,
the height of passion in their relationship.
Finally, the man walks away.  That
reflects what really happened in their
relationship.  He modeled the figure of the
woman in the kiss after her.  She
is the kiss.  Heat.  Heat.  Heat.  Heat.
Heat.  Heat.  Heat.  Heat.  Heat.
Heat.  All those lovely people out there
, all those
friendly little people.  It was so luxurious and elegant, and
they had these curtains, you know,
she loved blue, and she had
these really thick blue velvet curtains
, and they were perfect for
wrapping you up, you know?  So
Christopher, Punch and I were...and
I was wrapping myself up and suddenly I
realized that he started to
slip away as I went in.  I
was thinking, "Where are you going?"  And he ran over to
where they usually sat, you know,
that person at the reception desk.  So
she ran over there, and
Mrs. Harkness went downstairs.  And it was
incredible, that two-piece suit
I think was like white and mustard, and her
hair was up.  And I was going crazy
because I couldn't get out from behind the curtains,
and they are very thick curtains;  So you
know, it's like you're holding them
down, the curtain.  So I was
hanging them up and she came downstairs,
looked at me and said hi, Charles.  He kept
walking and Christopher came back and said,
"I know what?"  He said hello.  She said, "
Oh, I should have stayed."  And you
missed it.
Yes.
I think the biggest trouble I got into
was the day I left
class alone when no one was looking and went upstairs
.  What's up there?
Let me explore the fourth floor.  Is there
a fifth floor? You know what?  The
red room.  I went to the rooftop.  I went to the rooftop
and opened the door, and it was like Darth
Vader and the Wizard of Oz.  And I saw the rooftop
of Harkness House and started doing,
ahem, "Boy Crazy Boy" from Westside Story
and living and running.  And I jumped onto the other
rooftop and I was, you know, spinning and
living and loving it.  I was out of
class.  That was the best part.  He was
free.  Well, the doors
suddenly opened.  Security, all the guys
were there and I said, "What? Oh
my God."  What happened was that she had
danced all the way to another
building, which was a
Middle Eastern embassy, ​​and she was on top of its
rooftop.  Yes. He was up on his
roof dancing and living, and
security, you know, was up at his
embassy.  You don't know what that is or
who it belongs to...
Yes, because at that moment I was right next to
Harkness.  I can't remember if that
's
Afghanistan or...
and you know that she...
I think Mrs. H had a lot to do
with me getting the genius.  Ah
, I played Hookie from Harkness with
his ABT and it was when the American Valley
Theater was on 57th Street because I
loved teaching Paraslavic,
Madame Paris Slavic and that's what the
teachers were like.  I left and toured with
the Whiz, and then after a year, I
came back and decided to take a class with
Madame Perry, and she said, "Excuse me,
Madame. Uh, I've been on tour and haven't
had a class in a year."  And he
looked at me and said, "Jalice, whose
fault is this?"